Okay, so a rough outline for today's class will start off by sort of layering on more
and more complexity.
We'll start off with a basic idea, which is a Markov process, or a Markov chain, for
those of you who might come across this before.
And then we'll start to introduce some of the perhaps less familiar ideas, which are
central to reinforcement learning.
First of all, by adding rewards in to give a Markov reward process, then by adding actions
in to give a Markov decision process.
And finally, we probably won't have time to actually talk about them, but they're in
the lecture notes, but those of you who are interested, there's a lot of extensions to
MVPs where we can move beyond these three settings and add in even more complexity like partial
observability and so forth.
So I'll begin with the basics.
I'll try not to kill myself today on any stage.
So the basic idea then is we're going to develop this formulaism, the Markov decision process.
What we're trying to cover here is if you remember in the last class, we talked about
agents and environments.
We have an agent, that's our algorithm, and that's the brain that we're trying to build.
And it's interacting with some worlds.
Some of this might be the real world for a robot, it might be, you know, the trading
environment for a trading agent, the factory floor for a factory or whatever.
And this environment, we want some description of that environment such that we can understand
it, start to apply some tools to it and really understand what it means to do reinforcement
learning in that setting.
And that's going to be the MDP.
And in this case, what we're going to start with is the case, the nice case, where the
environment is fully observable.
So we're told the state.
So this is the case where we see everything that there is to know about that environment,
all the relevant information is presented to our agent, nothing is hidden away.
And one way to think of this is that the current state that's given to the agent, it sort of
completely characterizes this process of the way in which the environment unfolds, depends
on some state, and we're told that state, we know that state, it's fully observed.
And the nice thing about this formulaism is that really almost all reinforcement learning
problems can be formalized in some way as a markup decision process.
So if you think about even some of these less familiar cases, for those of you who come
across them, these are things which people might not first of all think of as markup
decision processes, but the problem of optimal control, where you've got say some differential
dynamics describing some fluid and you want to find the optimal way to make your octopus
swim through this fluid, how do we actually deal with that?
Well there's an extension to MDPs that's actually a continuous markup decision process
with continuous actions.
Optimal control actually really deals with that case.
Again partially observed problems, not only can we think of MDPs to give us some intuition
into them, but actually any partially observed problem can be completely converted into an
MDP.
So it's not the case that these things fall outside of the framework of MDPs, they are
MDPs, they really are MDPs, and if you understand the basics, you can solve all of these problems
in principle.
Some of the simplest cases, which we'll deal with in a later class, or we'll talk about
the exploration-exploitation dilemma in reinforcement learning, are what's known as bandits.
This is a very common formalism that's used a lot at the moment, where you get just a
set of actions, you get to take an action, you get some reward for that action, and that's
the end of your task.
So this is like the task we talked about last week, where you present an advert to the user
on the internet, and that advert either gets clicked on or it doesn't, and you want to
be clicked on as much as possible.
And actually this is just a markup decision process with only one state.
So again, it's a special case of MDPs, if we can solve MDPs, we can solve all of these
different cases.
So it's really fundamental.
So what's the central idea to an MDP?
Well, we've really seen this in the last class, but it's such an important concept,
I'm just going to flash up this slide again, which is the markup property.
And again, the markup property, the central idea which we're trying to understand here
is this idea that you have some state, this random variable s, this is characterizing where
we are in our environment.
And if it has the markup property, then this basically tells us that the future is independent
of the past given the present.
In other words, what happens next in our environment depends only on our previous state, and not
on all the things which came before that.
Okay, so the state completely characterizes everything which we need to know, it captures
all the relevant information from the history.
And once you know this thing, you can essentially, if you have ST, what this tells us is you
can throw away everything which came before.
So the set of markup processes or the set of states that have this property, it's the
set of environments in which everything which we know about the system can be described
by this single state at the current time, and we don't need to retain everything that
we've ever seen, okay?
So one way to understand this is that for any problem with the markup property, for any
markup process, if you start in some state S, and you've got some successor state, S
prime, then you can actually define the probability that you'll transition from one of those states
to the next state.
So remember that this state which we are in characterizes everything about what will happen
next.
So that must mean that there's some well-defined transition probability that tells me that
if I was in this state before, there's some probability, given that I was in that state,
that I will transition to some next state.
There's some probability that if my robot is here, and I give it a little push, then
it will fall over to here, or maybe put a foot forward.
All of these things are completely characterized by the state it was in before, okay?
So this gives us our state transition probabilities, so it's the probability that if I'm in S,
I transition to S prime, and that gives us the probability that this random next state
will be this particular instantiation of the state S prime, given that the previous state
we were in, our current state of time, T, was this S.
Now once we have this idea of the transition probability matrix, we can form this into
a complete matrix that tells us, essentially, each row of this matrix tells us what would
happen for each state that I was in.
So if I start in state one, this tells me the probability that I'll end up in state
one here, state two here, state three here, all the way up to N states here.
So each row of this completely characterizes the transitions from one possible starting
place in this Markov process.
So this single matrix now gives me the complete structure to this Markov problem, tells me
from any state how likely am I to end up in any other state.
So you can imagine now that we can follow this through multiple steps and keep sampling
from this transition probabilities, and that will give us some draws from this Markov process.
So let's try and understand that a little bit more.
So now just formally, a Markov process is basically a random process, a process that
we're sort of sampling from iteratively.
So that basically, our definition for this is going to be it's a sequence of random states.
So a sequence of random states, S1, S2, going on in time, that has the Markov property.
That's the definition of a Markov process, it's just a sequence of states with a Markov
property.
And so all it requires to define this thing is a state space, S, this is the set of states
which we can be in, and our transition probabilities that characterize how we transition from one
state to the next.
And now this fully defines the dynamics of this whole system, there's some evolution
of our robot through this system, or of our trading agent through this environment, or
of our chess playing agent through the rules of the game.
All of these things can be defined, no actions yet, no rewards yet, but the dynamics can
be fully defined by a state space and a transition probability matrix.
Okay, that's the Markov process.
So, I think it always helps to make these things concrete.
So let's try and make this concrete for you guys.
So this is my cartoon illustration of when I imagine it's like to be sitting in my lectures.
And so we're just going to imagine there's only three classes you have to sit through.
If you get through all three classes then you don't have to manage to pass the class,
if only it was that easy, but anyway.
But the problem is there's all these distractions along the way, so you start off in the first
class and there's a 50% probability you'll make it through to the next class, there's
also a 50% probability that you guys will open up your laptops, start looking at Facebook.
Now if you look at Facebook, we all know that once you're in Facebook it's a little bit
addictive, so there's probably about a .9 probability that you'll just kind of self-transition
and keep looking at Facebook, keep looking at Facebook again, and then maybe after you
iterate around this thing for a few times there's a .1 probability that you'll actually
drop out of this Facebook and get back to the class and listen to the rest of the class.
Which point you might make it to the second class, unfortunately, you know, maybe we're
talking about something really tedious like Markov processes and then you feel a bit sleepy
and so there's maybe a 20% probability you fall asleep, but there's maybe an 80% probability
you make it through to the final class, at which point maybe you think, yeah, I'm doing
really well and you get a bit excited and go up to the pub.
Which means if you go to the pub, you drink a few beers, you might end up either regressing
back to class one or class two because of all the things you forget, or if you don't
go to the pub there's a 60% chance that you'll pass and then after that you can go to sleep
and everyone's happy.
And this sleep state represents a terminal state to the Markov process.
A terminal state doesn't need any special machinery, you can think of this as just a
self-loop and absorbing terminal state, it just needs looping round and round and round.
That's what the square represents.
By the way, there's a few more seats over here, I think, if anyone wants to just move
around, if you're okay, that's fine.
Okay, so now that we've got this student Markov chain, let's think about what it means
to take samples of this.
So what's a sample?
A sample is a sequence.
It's a sequence of states where we start, for example, in our class one and now we're
just going to take samples through the system, for example, one sample might look like this,
where we go class one, class two, class three, pass, fall asleep, okay, that's the nice
sample.
But you might also have another sample that's like class one, Facebook, Facebook again,
that's class one, that's class two, and then fall asleep.
You might have more complicated samples, some of them might go on and on for quite a long
time, these are variable length, each of these you could think of as a random sequence that
is sampled from these dynamics, okay, so that's what it means to have a random process is
that you get some random sequence that's drawn from a probability distribution over sequences
of states.
And the fact that it has the Markov property means that it can be described by one of these
diagrams, if you like, it can be described by saying from any state there's some probability
of transitioning to any other state, is that clear, good, okay.
And now we can look at the transition matrix for this problem, so the transition matrix
is fully described now over here, the transition matrix basically tells us for any one of these
states which we might have been in, what's the probability of transitioning to any other
one of these states.
So for example, if we consider class two here, and we look across this row here, this row
of the transition matrix basically tells us there's a 0.8 probability and 80% chance
of transitioning to class three, but if we go across there's also a 20% chance of transitioning
to the sleep state.
And we look at all of the rows together that fully describes the entire dynamics of the
system, and once we have this matrix, we're able to sample repeatedly from this matrix
and get our samples of these sequence of states after this Markov process.
Okay, question.
So these things will only work if the probability is going to stay constant in each state, how
do you make it such that if you were to, say, go to Facebook, then you have a reducing
probability each time?
Okay, so the question is how do we deal with modifications to these probabilities over
time?
So there's two answers to that.
One answer is that you can have a non-stationary Markov process, later we'll have MDP, so
non-stationary MDP.
In that case, what you can do is use the same kind of algorithms we use for the stationary
case, but incrementally adjust your solution algorithm to just kind of track the best solution
you've found so far.
The other answer is to say, well, the fact that you've got non-stationary dynamics just
makes it a more complicated Markov process.
But there's some, so you're imagining that there's probabilities that depend on how long
you've been in this state and so forth, so now you can augment this state, you can have
a more complicated Markov process that has like a counter that tells you how long you've
been in this Facebook state, and now you've basically got lots of different states depending
on whether you've been in Facebook once or twice or three times, and you can have an
infinite set of these, you can have a continuous set of these, all of these things are possible,
but they don't change the fundamental structure from this being a Markov process.
This is just a particular simple instantiation where we can see everything on one page, but
don't let that mislead you into thinking that Markov processes are necessarily small
or simple.
We can solve very, very complex Markov processes, and the rest of the course we'll see how
to solve MDPs, some of them have 10 to the 170 states will be one of the examples we'll
do later.
These could be very large and complex pieces with a lot of structure to them.
So far we haven't really talked about reinforcement learning at all, there's no rewards, there's
no action, so let's start to put in some of that machinery now.
The first and perhaps most important step is to add rewards, and so one way to think
of this is we're now going to create what's called a Markov reward process, which you
could think of as like a Markov process with value judgments.
There's some value judgments saying how good it is to be in some particular, there's some
value judgment saying how much reward will I have accumulated across some particular
sequence that we sampled from this Markov process.
So all we're going to do to add into our Markov process is we're going to add in two
things, so we had our state space S and our transition dynamics P, now what we're going
to add in is some reward, a reward function R and a discount factor gamma, and let's just
talk about what those are and make sure we understand them.
So the reward function first of all, this is something which tells us that if we start
in state S, if we're in some state, how much reward do we get from that state only?
This is just the immediate reward, how much reward do I get from that state at that moment?
And what we care about is maximizing the accumulated sum of these rewards, that's what we care
about in reinforcement learning.
So for the Markov reward process, we're going to start summing these things together over
time.
The R for now, it just tells us for one step, at that moment, if we're at time t in state
S, at time t plus one, we'll get this reward, it just tells us what will happen next.
So if we go back to our student Markov reward process, what we're going to do is we're just
going to add in some value judgments now and I'm just going to tell you that maybe you
don't enjoy sitting in the class, so let's call that minus two for each class, minus
two reward here, minus two, but if you pass at the end of the class, you get this big
juicy bonus of plus 10.
Facebook, maybe you get like minus one per step as your brain gets drained of any sanity
that you used to have before you went onto Facebook, and going to the pub, maybe the
beer tastes good and you get plus one.
These obviously subjective value judgments we're arbitrarily throwing into this.
And then what we care about is the total reward that we're going to get across a whole chain
here.
We don't just care about how much reward you get for being in one class, we care about
the fact that maybe you get minus two here, but if you follow through an entire sequence,
you might get minus two plus minus two plus minus two plus ten, and that's your overall
reward that you get for that sequence, that sample of the Markov reward process.
And so what we talk about is this quantity called the return.
So we call it the return G, that's kind of, you can think of as the goal.
The goal of reinforcement learning is to maximize the return, so G sort of stands for goal here.
And the goal here, the return, is the reward summed over all of the time steps infinitely
into the future, and the way that we control this return and make it finite is by using
a discount factor.
So we basically say we're going to discount by a factor of gamma at each time step going
into the future.
So we're going to get an immediate reward of R, of Rt plus one here, and then we're
going to get gamma, say, you know, point nine times the reward at time step t plus two plus
gamma squared, point nine squared times the reward at t plus three, and so on, all the
way to infinity.
Okay, and that's going to be our goal, our goal is to maximize the sum of all of these
rewards.
Yeah, question?
There's no expectation here, that's a good question, why is there no expectation here?
There's no expectation here because we're just talking about a random sample at the
moment.
So G is random, G is just one sample from our Markov reward process of the rewards that
we get going through that sequence.
Later in a couple of slides we'll look, we'll introduce the expectation, which is what we
actually care about.
So this discount factor then has to be something between zero and one, and it tells us if you
like the present value of future rewards, it tells you how much I care now about rewards
I'll get in the future.
So it kind of tells me that if I'm at time step ten, and I know I'm going to get a reward
at time step twenty, then I should get discount that an additional ten times, that's ten times
steps into the future, so we're going to discount ten more times.
So this thing has to be between zero and one, and zero kind of means maximally short-sighted,
like if you have a discount factor of zero, you basically zero anything beyond your current
time step, and you only look at that first reward, and if you have a discount factor
of one, that's maximally far-sighted, where you care about all rewards going infinitely
far into the future, and you just assume that your Markov process has the property that
eventually these things will all be finite, so you'll get zero, like in our absorbing
terminal state, you just get zero, zero, zero at the end.
So specifically the value of receiving reward r, k plus one times steps later, is gamma
to the k r, we'll just keep discounting again and again.
Yeah, let's go back to our fly-out side of problems, like financial problems.
Okay, well, I'm going to have a slide on this, so.
So really, why should we do this?
It's basically, you know, we're somehow introducing a judgment here, which is that we prefer short-term
reward to delayed reward, we prefer reward now to reward later, and the amount that we
prefer reward now to reward later is given by gamma, so the closer it is to zero, the
more we prefer reward now, and the closer it is to one, the more indifferent we are to
when those rewards arrive.
So why should that be?
That was essentially the question, why should we do that?
So I'm going to turn that over to the audience, so in most of reinforcement learning, we use
a discount factor, so I just want to ask you guys, well, why, why should we do this?
Do you want to think of reasons?
Okay, great.
So someone said there's more uncertainty into the future.
I think that's a really great answer, actually.
So one reason to use a discount factor is to basically represent the fact that we do not
have a perfect model, so if you imagine that we're just building a Markov process to model
the environment, we're building this Markov reward process, but we don't have a perfect
model of the environment, so we think we've come up with some great plan, we think we
know exactly how much reward we're going to get into the future, but if we don't entirely
trust our decisions that we make, if we don't entirely trust our evaluations, we might choose
to discount because we might say, okay, well, maybe I can take this pot of gold now, or
maybe I should really trust my plan and my model that's going to tell me that all these
things are going to happen over the next 10 years and then I'll get an even bigger pot
of gold, or you have to really trust your model to wait all those time steps and really
believe that things are going to turn out just as you planned in order to get that bigger
pot of gold later.
So uncertainty, I think, is really one of the major kind of intuitive reasons to discount.
Any other points?
Any other ideas?
Yeah?
When you're trying to plan for the future, you're very fast, right?
So if you have that, some go to infinity, but the tension there is, maybe it's unbounded.
So we'd like to keep the people's, when they know that there's going to be some...
Right.
There are different levels.
Okay, absolutely.
So to keep the maps bounded, I mean, and actually, so I'll do my first...
A couple of slides here.
So, I mean, the first reason is just mathematically convenient, and I think, honestly, that's the
main reason we do it in the MDP framework for RL.
Most of the time, it's just because the maths all works out, it's easy to teach, it's easy
to understand, and it avoids these infinite returns.
So if you have some cycle in your markup process and you just get rewards again and again and
again and again, you need some mechanism to avoid infinity as your evaluation, otherwise
the maths just doesn't work out.
And there are other mechanisms for dealing with that, which we'll mention briefly.
We have the uncertainty, and I just want to go out into a couple of other ideas.
So someone mentioned already the idea that financial settings, it's rather natural.
So that's a quite specific setting, but in a financial setting, we have this idea of
interest rates that you kind of know that money now is worth more than money later, and
that's usually built into the definition of what it means to kind of make financial
decisions or trading system or whatever.
So that's a specific case where there's really a meaning to this, that you can think of gameras
like the inverse of the interest rate.
But one more point I just want to make is that actually, you know, animals and humans,
they actually show a preference for immediate rewards.
So people have done tests on humans, and it turns out that humans have not quite an exponential
discounting, but they have something like a hyperbolic discounting, but certainly animals
and humans do prefer to get reward now than reward later, and so you can think of this
as a cognitive model as well of how biological decision-making operates.
And finally, I just wanted to mention that if you don't agree with these points, which
I think is perfectly legitimate, to say, well, hey, look, you know, the problem I care about
really is artificial to introduce a discount factor, I'm only doing it to make it convenient.
There are alternatives, and there's undiscounted Markov reward processes.
The simplest case being where we know that all sequences terminate.
So if we go back to our student MRP, we know that all sequences ended up with, at some
point, falling asleep, one way or another.
And so if we know that's the case, then all sequences end, or at least end in this absorbing
terminal state which keeps getting zero and zero and zero again, and therefore, by definition,
all returns are finite.
And so then it's fine.
There's also a formulation that's in the extended notes for this class, which is the
average reward formulation, and there it's possible, even with infinite sequences, to
still deal with the undiscounted sort of evaluation of Markov processes and Markov reward processes
and MDPs.
Just to clarify, not all sequences terminate in the same way that there are infinite sequences,
but you can not end up in the same way.
No, that's not true.
So any single sample which you draw from this Markov process, by definition, is a finite
length.
There isn't some part of that process where I could just end up in a loop.
So any sample which you draw, there is, so it's impossible to draw a sample that's infinite.
Like by definition, the sample that you draw will terminate at some point.
That's the definition of this process.
And so even though the decision process itself contains infinite loops, any single sample
that you draw will be a finite length and will terminate, and the only question is at
what step it will terminate?
Okay.
Right, so now someone asked about expectations, and so this brings us to the value function,
which is really the central quantity which we're interested in RL.
So the value function, this is the quantity we really care about.
It's the long-term value of being in a state.
So if you're in this state S, so if you're in some concrete state S, how much value will
you get from there on?
The total reward that you'll get from that state onwards.
So formally, it's just the expected return if you start in that state.
So if I drop you into this Markov reward process in some state, like if I drop you in class
2, how much reward will you get from class 2 to the end until you terminate?
That's basically what it's saying.
How much reward will you get from then onwards?
And we have this expectation because the environment is stochastic.
We were in this stochastic Markov process.
The evolution of states might go one by one step, one episode, and another way the next
episode.
What we care about is the expected return over all of those different episodes.
And that's the value.
That's how good it is to be in any given state.
So this is the central quantity.
We prefer states.
We prefer to be in states that give us more total reward.
And so the formulation of our problem is to say, let's first of all just measure that.
So in an MRP, there's no concept of maximizing, we're just saying let's just measure how
much reward we'll get.
But when we get to MDPs, we want to maximize this quantity.
Okay, so let's get concrete again.
Let's go back to the student Markov chain, actually the student Markov reward process.
So the sample returns now.
So again, we're going to look at these samples of this process that we've taken, and we could
consider a discount factor of gamma equals 0.5.
So we basically halve the amount that we care about getting rewards every step.
And so this is the definition of our return, the gamma instantiate through the half.
And so now if we just look at the value of these guys, so these are basically like the
returns here.
So you get minus 2 at the first step, minus 2 discounted by a half, minus 2 discounted
by a quarter.
And then at the end of it, you've got this plus 10 reward for finishing the classes.
And that's discounted by an eight.
You sum those all together, you get minus 2.25.
So that's one sample of the return, so this guy should say G1.
And now we've got four different samples here.
And the different samples of first four, different sample sequences through this Markov reward
process.
So what's the value of being in this state?
What's the value of the start state?
Well, one way to estimate it is you can just take a bunch of samples and just take the
average of these values.
And that would give you a legitimate estimator for the value function, the value of that
state.
So the returns are samples, they're random.
But the value function is not a random quantity, it's an expectation over these random variables.
Okay, is that clear?
No, these subscripts are time steps.
So G1 is, so here we're basically saying, so the definition, we go back to the definition
of return, the definition of return was the return starting at time step t is the rewards
from that time step onwards.
Okay, so now we're considering a bunch of different returns.
We are also starting from S1 equal C1 in this case, but these things actually, the subscripts
are time steps.
And there are observed things, there's no expectation, because we're essentially saying
that we've observed these sequences.
These are observed samples of our random process.
And if we want to ask about the value function to make an expectation, we're asking, what's
the expected return?
What's the expected number that's going to pop out of this at the end?
What's the average of these numbers?
And that's how good it is to be in this first state of the student Markov chain.
Okay, so what does this look like?
So let's consider a couple of different discount factors.
So first of all, this is the maximally short-sighted view of the value function.
So this is the value function now for gamma equal 0.
This is where we literally don't care about anything except one step of immediate reward.
So if we take any given state here, so now if we consider class 2 state here, we know
that no matter what we do afterwards, we're going to get the reward of minus 2 at this
time step.
It doesn't matter that we're going to get these other things and this plus 10 later,
that's irrelevant because we're just looking at how much reward we get at this time step
onwards.
So the value of being in this state is minus 2.
That's what we're going to get.
We're going to get minus 2 whether we go to sleep or whether we go this way, we're going
to get minus 2.
That's just the definition of that.
However, if we look at a more long-sighted discount factor, so this is at 0.9 now, then
the values all change and now we have to consider, well, if I was in this state, I'm going to
get a reward of minus 2 now, but then with 0.8 probability, I'm going to transition
over here into a situation where I'm going to get additional rewards minus 2 and then
plus 10 again and so forth, and when we factor that all together on computer and we'll see
how to compute these things later as we go on, the value of this state actually becomes
much better.
We can get 0.9 reward from this state onwards, averaging over the probability of falling
asleep and continuing through to classes.
So that's the value.
That's the average.
Now, the expectation over all of the different paths that we can take through this system
and take an average of them, that's the number that summarizes how good it is to be in that
state.
So that's 0.9 units of reward from then onwards if we start there.
If I drop you into that class, 0.9, that's how good you are.
So now we're going to talk about maybe the most fundamental relationship in reinforcement
learning.
I might have come across this in dynamic programming, it's very widely used, and it's called the
Bellman equation.
And the idea is that the value function sort of obeys this recursive decomposition, and
the main idea is very simple, that it basically says that you can take your sequence of rewards
from this time step all the way onwards, and you can break it up into two parts, which
basically consists of the immediate reward that you're going to get, and then the value
that you'll get from that time step onwards.
So you break it up into immediate reward, and then from the successor state that you
end up in, the value of where you end up, so immediate reward plus the value of where
you end up.
Now if I'm a robot, I might get an immediate reward of like plus 10, but then I end up
in this new state, and the question is how good is it to be in this new state?
And so the overall value function of being here is like my 10 points of immediate reward
plus the value of where I ended up, and that's what the Bellman equation tells me.
So formally if we just step through this, it's very straightforward, so this is our
value function.
The value function is the expected return, given that I start in a particular state.
And that's how we want to know how good is it to be in this state, and it's the expected
return if you start in that state.
We just unwrap the definition of return.
The return is just the sum of these rewards going into the future, discounted.
We can break down those sum of rewards into the immediate reward plus the discounted value,
the discounted return from the next step.
So we've got a discount, we just pull out the discount factor we've got, starting from
RT plus 2 plus gamma RT plus 3, and so forth, okay, just pull the factor of gamma out.
And now we see that this thing here is just the return from the next time step, the return
starting from T plus 2 instead of from T plus 1.
So that's this thing here, we say it's the expected immediate reward plus discounted
return.
And then by the law of iterated expectations, what we can do is basically say the expectation
of this return is the same as the expectation of this return, that's called the law of iterated
expectations, which gives us this final line here, which tells us that the value function
in state S is equal to the expected immediate reward plus the value function of the next
state.
Yeah, question?
I'm slightly confused with the indexes here, like when we start between state S and T,
but the time is T, and we encounter the first reward, like T plus 1.
Okay, so the question is why do we index the reward at time T plus 1?
Actually you'll find both in the literature.
We're following the Satin Abate Convention, which indexes rewards at time step T plus
1 rather than time step T.
This comes from how we think of the boundary between agent and the environment, that the
idea is that the action that we take goes into the environment, then a time step happens
whilst that we switch our time index after control passes back from the environment to
the agent, we're in a new time step.
So at that point, everything we receive from the environment has a new time index.
So everything after the environment has a time step T plus 1.
You might even find that my slides might be slightly inconsistent on this point, so it's
a good spot.
So I'm sorry if that's the case.
Yeah.
Actually, if you define it that way, when gamma equals 0, the actual value of the state
won't be the immediate reward, because it will be the probability that, like, if you
go to the slide, the gamma equals 0, the actual value of the state is going to be different
from there, I think.
No, that's not true.
It's just a difference.
It's literally just re-indexing.
So you can re-index everything with RT instead of RT plus 1, it's not going to change any
format than any of the semantics.
It's all the same.
So, yeah.
In the previous slide, the reward, the zero discounting was the reward in the state that
I'm currently in.
If you set gamma to zero here, it looks like the reward in the state I'm currently in is
the expected reward at the next stage.
And just...
Yeah.
So ...
Yes.
Yeah.
It's just a convention, so don't confuse yourselves.
It's just a convention.
Stick to the very intuitive idea, you move into a state,
you get some reward, everything is good.
So let's just try and understand this Bellman equation
a little bit more.
So the Bellman equation, so this is our Bellman equation.
The value function now is equal to the expected immediate
reward plus discounted value at the next state.
Value now, take a step, see what the value is
in the state I end up.
And that's just like a tautological definition.
If we've got our value function correct,
it must obey this identity.
That's what it means to have a value function.
If we don't obey this identity, we haven't found
the value function yet.
So one way to understand this is by using what we call
these backup diagrams here.
So these backup diagrams, this is basically showing us,
you can think of this as like a one step look ahead search.
We start in this state s, and we can look ahead
one step if you like.
So this state s leads to a value function of a v of s.
If we go down to s prime here or here,
we're going to have a value function that's v
of the successor state, and we're going to get some
immediate reward along the way.
So this diagram is just kind of showing us that we can
think of this as a one step look ahead tree,
where you start in this state, you look ahead one step,
you integrate over the probability of each of these
functions here.
So it's a one step look ahead with like this averaging,
where we kind of go ahead one step, we average all the
possible outcomes together, and that gives us the value
function of this step.
And that's actually kind of the way that we're going to
proceed when we actually start to build algorithms.
They're going to do something like this look ahead process,
which is why it's useful to have these backup
diagrams in mind.
OK, so if we think about the value function now,
let's just pick out one state.
So if we pick out this state here, so this is the
class three state.
And so I'm just going to tell you that this is going back.
I think this is a discount factor of one now.
So it's undiscounted.
And what we're looking at is what happens if we're in this
state with no discounting.
So I claimed that this was the value function of this
MDP, but how can we verify that?
Well, we can use the Bellman equation to verify that.
We can say, OK, well, if this value function is 4.3, it
should really be equal to doing like a one step look
ahead, averaging over all the things which might happen
next, and then ending up back here again.
So let's see if that's really true.
Well, from here, there are two things which could happen.
So we could either basically get minus 2 immediate reward
no matter what happens.
That's just minus 2 here.
And then with 0.6 probability, you're going to move
through to the next class and end up somewhere
with a value of 10.
But there's also 0.4 probability that you'll go
to the pub, and you'll end up in this state which had a
value of 0.8.
So if we sum those things together, we get minus 2
plus 0.6 times 10 plus 0.4 times 0.8, which to numerical
precision is 4.3.
And so that's validated the fact that this really is the
value of this MDP.
And then here, what is this capital power
represents?
Is this the reward for doing this step?
This is?
OK, so I think I need to be clear about the rewards.
So let me try and explain that whole clearly.
What this diagram represents is that you're in some state.
When you exit that state, regardless of what you do,
you will get the reward indicated by this R.
So upon exiting that state, regardless of where you end up,
you'll get this minus 2.
So we could have duplicated this and written R minus 2
here, R minus 2 here, and it could have been on these arcs.
And actually, when you define Markov decision processes,
which we'll see later, and for Markov reward processes, you
can make it dependent on the particular arc that you take.
You can make it dependent on the action.
You can make it dependent on the successor state.
All of these things are possible.
This is the simplest formulation.
The rewards just depend on the state that you're in.
And that state determines how much immediate reward you'll get.
And then you have to look at where
you ended up to see how much immediate reward you'll
get on the next step.
So you start here.
You exit it.
You get minus 2.
You get to here.
You exit this state.
You get minus 2.
You get R equals 0.
Sorry, guys.
You get plus 10.
You exit this state.
Repeatedly, you get 0, 0, 0, 0, 0.
Yeah, last question.
Then I'll move on.
Is there a reason why one needs to exit the past state
to get the reward of what's done in the future?
Yes.
Yes, thank you.
OK, let's move on.
OK, so this Bellman equation, so far we've
seen how to spell this out literally state by state.
But there's a much more concise formulation,
which is using matrices and vectors.
So if we just spend a moment to understand that, what we can do
is basically use this matrix formulation of the transition
matrix, which we've already seen.
But now what we're going to do is
we're going to introduce a vector representation
of the value function, which is the obvious thing.
It's basically we form a column vector,
where each element of the column vector
contains the value function of a specific state for all states
from 1 to n.
And so now we can write out our Bellman equation very
concisely.
It's just that the value function that you start with,
this column vector here, is equal to,
and we're going to do the same thing with the reward function
as well.
We're going to write out the reward function with one
element per state.
This tells us how much reward you'll get from exiting state 1,
all the way down to how much reward you'll get from exiting state
n, so forth.
So this is your immediate reward.
And then this is how much, this is where you'll transition to.
And this is how much value you started with before.
So it's basically telling us that in one sweep,
we can just look at this thing and say the value of their state
is equal to the immediate reward plus the transition matrix.
So these are all the places we might transition to.
And then this is the value of where we end up.
This is the value of after I take this step,
I might end up in this state, I might end up in this state,
I might end up in this state.
And each row of this thing is going
to be dot-productive with these values.
There's some probability if I'm in this state
that I end up in each of these successor states.
And then we take the dot product of that
with all of the values of where we end up.
And that's going to give us this first entry here.
So it gives us, literally, it's a way
of writing out the entire Bellman equation in one
very concise form.
OK.
Yeah, question?
The Bellman equation is number one.
Yes, that should be pn1, actually, from the bottom left.
OK.
So the Bellman equation is a linear equation.
As a result, it can be solved directly.
It's one of the nice things about linear equations.
This is not going to be true once we move to the more complex case
with Markov precision processes.
It's a nice property of just evaluating the rewards.
But once we want to maximize rewards,
it's super gets harder.
But at this stage, at least, we can solve this directly.
Assuming that our matrix is small enough to invert,
what we can do is just write out our linear equation now.
All we're going to do is collect together the v terms here.
So we've got identity times v here and gamma p times v here.
So we collect those together on this side, i minus gamma p,
v equals r, and then we just invert this matrix.
OK.
And this is the solution to the MDP.
The computational complexity of inverting this matrix
is n cubed for n states.
So this is not typically a practical solution method
for large Markov processes.
So what we'll start to look at in subsequent lectures
is efficient ways to solve these problems.
In particular, this is just going to be a building block.
All of the things we've seen so far
are just building blocks towards what we really care about,
which is making decisions.
And so this is just going to be a building block.
We need to be able to efficiently figure out
what's the value of being in this state.
We can't always do this.
But it is nice to know that as well, Markov reward processes,
we can just invert this thing.
And it gives us some intuition into what's going on.
So later, we'll talk about the next lecture, in fact.
The next class is dynamic programming.
That's a very well-known class of methods
for basically doing this more efficiently.
Then we'll talk about Monte Carlo evaluation
and temporal difference learning.
That's like the next couple of lectures
are basically doing exactly that.
Right.
So that was sort of the elementary building
blocks leading up to this point, which is the MDP.
This is the thing which we actually
do in reinforcement learning.
And so I guess I should pause.
Any questions so far?
I guess we've been doing them as we go, so.
Right.
So the MDP, we're basically going to add in one more piece
of complexity now, which is actions.
So so far, there's been nothing for us to do.
I just told you, you get plunked down
in your student Markov reward process.
And you just randomly sell up all these transitions
and get spat out at the other end.
You didn't get any, you didn't have any agency.
You weren't able to take actions and make decisions.
So let's now change that.
Let's introduce decisions.
So what we're going to do now is basically
take our Markov reward process, which
was a state space transition matrix, reward function,
and discount factor, and add in one more component, which
is the action space.
So A is now a finite set of actions.
In the extensions to the class, you'll
see how this can be made continuous or infinite.
But now we'll consider the simplest case.
This is a discrete set of actions, finite size.
And so now what we're going to do is
say the transition probability matrix now
depends on which action we take.
So where you end up is now going to depend
on the action that you take.
You take, if you move to the left,
the probability that you end up in all these different states
is going to be different if you choose to move to the right.
The wind might blow you different ways in each case,
but you have some agency over where you're going to end up.
So the way we think of this is that there's just one,
in the discrete case, there's like one separate matrix
of transition probabilities for each action that you might take.
And now we've got this reward function.
The reward function, again, may depend on the action.
It may also not depend on the action, but in general,
this thing can depend on the action.
Apart from that, everything is the same.
The machinery is the same.
We've just introduced actions in the simplest possible way.
So what we're going to do is actually
redo our student marker process now, but as an MDP,
where there's decisions that you can take.
So the decisions are now these red labels on the arcs.
And so the point now is that you actually
have some agency here.
And so from this state, you can choose to either study.
That's a choice now, so there's no probabilities attached to this.
You can choose to study.
If you study, you end up in the state.
If you choose to go to Facebook, you end up in this state.
When you're at Facebook, you can choose to do it again,
or you can choose to quit.
You can choose to go to sleep here, or to study again.
You can choose to study again, or you can choose to go to the pub.
If you choose to go to the pub, that's the only place now
in that there's any randomness.
If you choose to go to the pub, who knows what might happen?
Maybe you'll drink one or two beers, not quite sure.
So now there's some probability that you'll end up going back
to class one, going back to class two,
or even going back to class three.
So there's a lot more control that you can exert now
over your path through this MDP.
This is the reality for an agent.
And the goal is, the game we're playing now
is to try and find the best path through your decision-making
process that maximizes the sum of rewards that you get.
That's the game that you play in an MDP.
So to do that, the first thing we need to talk about
is formalizing what it means to make decisions,
and to take decisions.
And to do that, we define something called the policy.
So the policy is basically, we're
going to talk about stochastic policies today.
And these policies are distributions over actions
given states.
So in other words, if you're in some state S,
this distribution basically gives you the mapping.
It says, if I'm in this state, map from that state
to some probability of going left
and some probability of going right.
So this is the thing that tells me, if I'm in class 1,
I am going to choose to go to class 2 with probability 0.9.
It's going to Facebook with probability 0.1.
This is something under the agent's control.
It's something we decide.
And it's just a stochastic transition matrix.
And it's useful to make it stochastic,
because that allows us to do things like exploration.
So we'll make use of that later in the course.
So once you have a policy, it completely
defines how that agent will behave.
And in an MDP, the policies depend just on the current state.
That was the Markov property.
Doesn't depend on the history.
And as a result, we consider what we call stationary policies.
We don't consider all of the policies the same no matter
what time step we're in in the MDP.
We just have the same policy at each time step.
And the only thing that this depends on
is the state that we're in, not the time step at which it
happened.
And that's sufficient to behave optimally,
because by definition, we have the Markov property.
And this state, S, fully characterizes everything
that will happen next.
Yeah, question?
How do we reward the element here?
And I'm sure you want to maximize rewards
in terms of the fact that they're not.
The question was, why are there no rewards in this equation?
And that's because the state, S, fully characterizes
your future rewards.
So in a Markov reward process or Markov decision process,
the Markov property means that S fully characterizes
the evolution from this state onwards in the process.
And so what you're looking for is the policy, which,
given the state you're in, well, you
want to pick actions that will get you the most future reward.
So all you need to look at is what state am I in
and what action should I take next?
And we're trying to pick those actions in the way,
given that state, that will get us the most future reward.
So the rewards are in the future.
We don't care about how many rewards we've got in the past.
Those rewards have gone now.
They've been consumed.
All we care about is how much reward
we can get from now into the future.
So we don't actually care when we try to maximize this thing.
We don't care if we currently, if we've already
achieved a million reward or minus a million reward.
That's irrelevant.
What we want to do is maximize the reward from now onwards.
That's the way we're going to behave optimally.
I would give commission on state information-wise
to produce all the information that I would
expect to be the reward state.
Yes.
Yes, exactly.
OK.
So one important thing to note about the connection
between Markov decision processes and Markov reward
processes is that we can always recover an MRP or a Markov
process from our decision process.
So just to understand that, we can
think about basically the sample of states that we draw.
Like if we have some policy that helps us pick actions,
we're just going to draw this sequence of states.
And the sequence of states that we draw,
when we follow our particular process,
is actually a Markov chain, so a Markov process itself.
No matter what policy we choose, that policy defines
some Markov chain that actually defines our dynamics the way
that we're going to move through and evolve through this system.
And if we look at the sequence of states and rewards
that we receive as we pass through,
like once we fix the policy, if you fix the policy
and look just at the sequence of states and rewards that you see
as you go through this MDP, that sequence
is a Markov reward process.
And the way to understand that is
that we're going to define basically transition dynamics
and reward function with just average over our policy.
We're just going to average over all the things which
happen under our policy.
We're going to average over.
So we're going to define the transition dynamics
to be the average of the transition dynamics for all
of the things that we might do.
So if we're going to go left with probability 0.5
and right with probability 0.5, I'm just
going to take 0.5 times the dynamics,
or all the probability of going to all the states from here,
plus 0.5 times the probability of all the states
that I'm going to end up in over here.
Sum those together, and those average dynamics
define some Markov reward process.
So we can always flatten our MDP given our current policy
back into a Markov chain.
This is just a useful point.
It's not like central.
So you can come back to this and think about it offline
if you like.
OK, what is central is the concept of the value function.
So we already had the value function
for a Markov reward process, but there was no agency there.
There was no decisions.
Now we've got this policy.
There's some way that we can choose
to behave in our Markov process.
I might be following this path straight through the student
Markov chain where I collect all the rewards
by going through all the classes,
or I might choose to spend a lot of time on Facebook.
These are going to give different rewards.
There's not one expectation anymore.
There are different expectations depending on how I behave.
And so we subscript our value function
by the policy that we're interested in evaluating.
So v pi of s now tells us how good is it to be in state s
if I'm following policy pi?
So if I'm following the policy that just
goes straight through the classes,
how much reward will I get?
Or if I'm following the policy where I stay on Facebook
for as long as possible, how much reward
will I get from each state on this?
So this basically is defined.
We've just got this expectation here now.
This e pi basically means the expectation
when we sample all actions according to this policy pi.
That's sort of hidden in that e pi notation.
We're also going to define a second type of value function
called the action value function.
So so far we've got the state value function.
This v we call the state value function
that tells us how good is it to be in a particular state s.
We're also going to define the action value function
which tells us how good is it to take a particular action
from a particular state.
And this is the thing which we intuitively care about
when we want to decide which action should I take?
Should I go left or should I go right?
Well, I should choose the one that's
going to give me more reward.
And the way I evaluate these things
is by looking at the action values.
In other words, we're basically going to look at,
so q pi, so for a given policy, for a given way to behave,
we want to know if I'm in this state s
and I take this action a, what's the expected return,
the total reward that I'll get after I've taken that action,
how much reward will I get from that point onwards?
OK, that's the key quantity that we're
going to use to help us optimize our MDP
and pick the best actions.
So let's make this concrete again.
So this is the state value function for the student MDP,
undiscounted, so the discount factor is 1.
And this is just for uniform random behavior.
So we're fixing the policy to say,
we're always, when we've got a choice,
we're always going to randomly pick
50-50 between those choices.
And so this is the value function that we end up with.
We see that we end up thinking it's not very good to start
in this state here because there's
a high probability of ending up in the Facebook state
because we're choosing things 50-50.
Now what we can define is another Bellman equation.
So the Bellman equation, we saw this in the Markov reward
process, and now we're going to define a Bellman equation
for these value functions in the MDP case.
So again, we can use the same idea,
that the value function can be decomposed
into an immediate reward plus the discounted value
at the next state.
So again, there's this idea that wherever you are,
you take one step, and you get your immediate reward
for that step, and then you look at the value of where
you end up, and the sum of those things together
tells you how good it was to be in your original state.
That's still true in an MDP.
Now what we're saying is that you start in this state,
and we know that we're following policy pi,
but the value thing in this state
is still the immediate reward that you get
plus the value of your successor state,
if you know that you're going to follow policy pi
from there onwards.
So we just look at what happened for one step
of following a policy, and then we ask,
how much more reward will I get following that policy?
And we sum those things together,
that gives us the Bellman equation.
We can do the same thing with the action value function,
with these Q values, and this basically tells us,
now, if I'm in one state, and I take an action from there,
then I'll get some immediate reward for that action,
for that specific action, and then I'll look at
where I end up, and I can ask, well,
what's the action value of the state that I end up in
under the action that I would pick from that point onwards?
So let's look at these kind of pictorially
and try and understand them with these
sort of look ahead search diagrams.
So the way to understand this is, first of all,
to understand how V and Q relate to each other.
So if you're in a state value function here,
really what it's saying is that we're gonna average over,
basically we're gonna average over the actions
that we might take.
So the sub-probability that we'll take this action here,
these black dots represent actions,
and these open circles represent states now.
So we're in some state here.
We might take this action here,
we might take this action here.
The probabilities of these things are defined
by our policy.
So this is like the probability I'll go left,
the probability I'll go right.
Over each of those actions we might take,
there's a Q value, there's an action value
telling us how good it is to take that action
from that state.
And so we're doing like a one step look ahead,
saying the state value, how good it is to do this state,
we just look ahead one step, look at the action values,
average them together, and that tells us the value
of being in that state at the top there.
Now let's do the converse, understand the opposite step.
So what happens if we start off taking some action?
So now the root of this tree is a state,
and we're considering a specific action
that we take from that state,
that's this black circle here.
So this is like saying I'm in this particular state here,
and I'm considering, I'm asking the question,
how good is it to go right from that state?
And how good it is, we now have to average
over the dynamics of our MDE,
the environment might blow me over here,
so after I've gone right,
I might get blown to all these different situations,
and we want to ask for each of these situations
I might get blown to, how good is it?
What's the value of being in that situation
following my policy after that point?
We average over all these things,
using the probabilities of our transition dynamics,
we average them together,
and that gives us the action value function
of the roots here.
Okay?
So V is telling us how good is it to be in a particular state,
Q is telling us how good is it
to take a particular action from a given state,
state value function, action value function.
We can put these together now,
so this is basically just stitching together
the two figures from the last two slides,
and now what we'll see is we get like a recursion
that helps us understand V in terms of itself,
and this is how we end up solving
Markov decision processes.
So at the roots of the tree now,
we've got the value function for a particular state,
tells us how good is it to be in this state,
and the way we're gonna understand that
is by doing a two-step look ahead.
So if we look ahead, we could consider
all the actions we might take next,
go left, go right,
we could consider all the things
that the environment might do to us,
might blow me over, it might keep me standing up,
there are all the things the environment might do,
and then for each of those things the environment might do,
there's some successor state that we'll end up in,
we want to know well how good is it to be in that state
and carry on with my usual policy,
how much reward will I get if I carry on from that point.
Now if we average these things all together,
we're basically averaging in two ways,
now we're averaging over our policy,
we're weighting each of these arcs by the probability
that a policy will select left or right,
we're averaging each of these arcs
by the transition probabilities
that will end up getting blown in one direction or another,
we average it all together,
and that gives us the value of being
in the root of this diagram here,
tells us how good is it to be in a particular state.
So this is the Bellman equation.
You can do exactly the same thing for action values,
there's a recursive relationship,
you can look at this offline,
I don't want to sort of belabor the point,
but it's just stitching the diagram together
the other way around,
and we end up with exactly the same idea
that starting from a particular state in action,
we can now look ahead two steps,
consider where the wind might blow us first now,
and then consider from the state
the wind might blow us to,
which action might I take next?
Am I choose to go left or am I choose to go right?
And now we average over this thing again,
we look at the value of that particular action,
the Q value, average these things all together,
and it tells us something about the Q value
of this start action here.
So the Q value relates to the Q values of the next step,
in this slide, and the previous slide,
the state values here,
relates to the state values of the next step.
So you get these two recursive relationships,
explaining how the value function relates
to itself of the next step.
In all of these cases,
if you just look beneath the map,
the math, it's a very simple idea,
which says the value function at the current time step
is equal to the immediate reward,
plus the value function of where you end up.
That's all these things are saying,
just with different ways of putting together the maths.
Okay, so let's do that for one example
in our student MDP.
We'll move on a little bit.
So here's our student MDP again.
We're gonna consider just one state,
this red state here, so the class three state.
And again, I'm just gonna verify,
we're not kind of compute using this Bellman equation
to compute these value functions.
We're gonna use it to verify
that this indeed does have the value of 7.4, okay?
So how can we verify it?
Well, we can unroll, we can do our look ahead,
and what we're gonna do is we're gonna do our look ahead
for the state value function here.
So we're saying the state value function 7.4
is equal to all the things which we might do from there.
So what are the things we might do from there?
Well, we might study.
Remember, we're doing things 50-50 with the,
for now with 50% chance we choose to study it,
50% chance we go to the pub.
So under that policy where we do everything 50-50,
so yeah, this whole diagram is showing us the value function
for the policy where we choose all of our decisions 50-50.
And under that policy, we start in this state,
there's a 0.5 chance we'll take this arc
and get plus 10 reward, that's this part here.
There's also a 0.5 chance we'll end up taking this arc,
end up in the pub, and the pub might take us
with 0.2 probability over here,
0.4 probability over here, 0.4 probability over here.
And in each of those cases, we'll end up in a different state
with a different value.
So there's a 0.2 chance we'll end up in this value state here
with value minus 1.3,
there's a 0.4 chance we'll end up in this state
with a value of 2.7,
and the 0.4 chance we'll end up in this state here
with a value of 7.4 again and end up where we started.
So you can see this is quite cyclic, this thing.
And so that's this equation here,
we just sum those things together.
So we're summing together this look ahead
of what might happen after one step of taking actions
and one step of where we end up.
And when you add this together,
so one decimal place you get 7.4.
So we've sort of verified that these numbers
are self-consistent for this one state,
you can verify them for all of the other states
and you would discover that this Bellman equation
does indeed hold,
and therefore these numbers do represent
the value function for this end of here.
So that basically tells us now we really know
how good is it to be in each one of these states,
but you really will get 7.4 units of reward
in expectation if you just behave according to this policy.
Okay, is that clear?
Right, so that's all very well,
but it doesn't tell us the best way to behave.
And what we really care about in MDP
is figuring out the best way to behave.
So, okay, just briefly before we do that.
So I briefly introduced earlier,
and I said it wasn't essential,
but this idea that you could flatten any MDP
back into a Markov reward process
by defining these averaged state transition dynamics
and averaged reward function.
And of course, once we've averaged those things,
that gives us a Markov reward process,
we know how to solve those things already.
So at least one way to solve that,
another way to have solved for these numbers
would have been to form these matrices,
form the matrix of our transition probabilities
for all of our actions,
average them together to get our p pi,
average together our immediate rewards to get our r pi,
solve for this equation here,
and that would have sped out our actual value function.
So that's one way to arrive at the solutions,
and we'll look at more efficient ways to do it
on going into the future.
But you should at least understand the idea
that the Bellman equation gives us
a description of the system that we can solve.
Once we solve for this thing,
it tells us exactly what the value function is.
So one linear equation we solve it,
you've got the value function, you're done.
Right, now, for the last half an hour,
I want to talk about the essential problem
we really care about,
which is finding the best behavior in the NDP.
I'll just pause for a moment, just to start.
Sorry, I know there's a lot of material,
so any questions at this point?
People tracking?
Are you going to put the newest ones online?
I'll put the newest ones online immediately afterwards, yeah.
So there's mostly notation change.
Change the notation to match the new addition
of such a combata.
Can you just explain again what happened to the state pub,
which seems to have turned into some other...
It used to be a state, right?
Yeah, so when we moved from the Markov reward process
to the Markov decision process,
we changed the definition of the problem.
So the pub used to be a state,
now it's a decision that we're making.
We're taking a decision now.
So we're making these decisions of whether to go to a pub
or whether to study.
So it's actually a different problem
that we're studying now.
So a pub is an action, yeah.
Here, a pub is an action, yeah.
But it ends up with something which isn't a state,
whereas a study ends up with something which is a state,
so what?
No, everything ends up in a state.
So if you take the pub action,
you end up at this black dot represents
like a chance mode.
Even you can't stay there.
You can't stay there, no.
The action takes you to here,
and the environment immediately transitions you
to here, to here, or to here with these probabilities.
So you can think of this as basically telling you the dynamics.
So if you take this pub action,
you're basically going to be teleported
to here, here, or here.
You'll get a plus one reward along the way,
and the probability of ending up here, here, or here
is given by these numbers.
That's what it means.
Okay, why did you do that?
I don't understand, but why did you now have
this separate sort of transient state?
Because I wanted to illustrate an example
where you have some agency,
we have some control over what happens in the environment,
and now it's a choice whether to go to the pub or not.
And the randomness is now what happens
after you go to the pub.
So all the other states could be considered
to be the same as that, but with just probability
and one of going to there.
Exactly, everything.
You can implicitly imagine there's one of these black dots
in every one of these other arcs.
So if you go to Facebook, there's a black dot here
that says the action is taking you to that black dot,
but that black dot is always taking you here
with probability one.
And actually now, let's say that action
has a reward earlier on,
we were saying only that the state has a reward,
and now that's an action.
Yeah, we go back, this was all in the definition of MDP.
So if we go back to the definition of MDP,
the red highlights here indicate what changed
from the Markov reward process.
And one of the things that's changed
was that the reward function was now indexed
by both state and action.
So the reward does depend on the action you take.
That's the definition on MDP.
Okay, so what you do might affect the immediate reward
you get as well as the state you end up in.
So sometimes there's a cost to the action you take,
that's the simplest case.
Like imagine a trading agent,
you buy a thousand pounds of goods from someone,
that immediately costs you a thousand pounds
compared to the action of do nothing, which costs you zero.
So there's a cost associated with the specific actions,
and they take you to different states.
So that's really the commonest case.
So you should intuitively expect that rewards
have different effects depending on
the particular action you take.
The difference with non-determinism,
really, is to possibly taking an action
but ending up probabilistically
in one of a number of different states.
And MDP is stochastic, and MDP is stochastic.
The stochastic transitions depend
on the action that you take.
So you get to take an action,
the environment gets to throw the dice
and tell you where you end up.
So it's a combination of your actions
and the dice which get rolled by the environment
which determine what happens next.
Okay, good.
Okay, so now let's talk about
how to find the best possible solution to the MDP.
So what we really want,
we don't really care about how much reward
we'll get following this crazy 50-50 policy
in the student Markov chain.
What we care about is finding the best path
through the system.
In general, you want to find the optimal way
to solve your problem.
And so let's define what that really means now.
And so we're gonna start with value functions.
We're basically going to say this V star,
the optimal state value function, V star,
is the maximum value function over all policies.
So what we're saying is there's all kinds
of different policies we could follow in our Markov chain.
And what we care about is the best of those.
We care about understanding what's the maximum possible
amount of reward that you can extract from the system.
There's all these different ways
you can traverse the system.
Each of your different policies
is gonna lead to a different evolution.
Stochastic evolution, we care about which of those
is going to lead to the most reward in expectation.
That's, V star tells you not what the best policy was,
but what's the maximum possible reward
that you can extract from the system.
Similarly, the optimal action value function,
Q star, tells you the maximum amount of reward
you can extract starting in state S and taking action A.
So given that you actually commit to a particular action,
what's the most possible reward
you can get from that point onwards?
They start in some state,
you know that you can take the left,
but what's the maximum possible reward
you can get after you've moved left?
And what's really important about this guy here
is that if you know Q star, then you're basically done.
If you want to know the optimal way
to behave in your MDP, what would you do?
Well, if someone told you
the maximum possible amount of reward
you could get over all policies
given every action that you might take.
So this is basically telling you,
under all different ways you could behave,
if you go left, you might get 70 units of reward,
but under all different policies, if you go right,
you can get 80 units of reward.
Well, what do you do?
Which way do you go?
You go right, you get 80 units of reward
rather than 70 units of reward.
So this immediately tells you the right action to take.
If you have Q star, you're done.
You can kind of declare victory.
You've got the quantities necessary
to behave optimally within your MDP.
So we could say informally that MDP is solved
when we know this optimal value function.
So solving an MDP, you could think of as finding Q star.
So let's just look at that.
What is the optimal value function here?
So again, we're gonna look at the undiscounted case
just to keep the numbers simple.
And in this case, it should be fairly intuitive.
You can kind of even work this out just by eyeballing it,
that if you're in this state here,
should you go to the pub, should you study?
Well, if you study, you're gonna get this plus 10
big juicy reward and go to sleep.
So that turns out to be the optimal value.
We'll see more formally how to derive that in a minute.
If we go back up one state here,
we can either go to sleep and get a reward of zero
along the way, or we can study and end up
in this nice juicy state with a value of 10,
and get minus two along the way.
So the value of being here is eight.
We back up one state again.
We can see the value of being in this state is six,
because after a reward of minus two,
we'll end up in this state with eight.
So that's the optimal value that you can actually get.
This is V star in this MDP.
It tells you how good it is to be in each of these states.
And that tells you the most possible juice
you can extract from this MDP.
It doesn't yet tell you how to behave in it.
To do that, there's two things you can do.
Well, what we do is we basically define our Q stars now.
In order to figure out what's the best action to take,
we look at our action value function.
So the action value function is now labeling these arcs
with what's the value of each arc.
So it's saying what's the optimal value of each arc.
So we know, for example,
the optimal value of this arc here, that's 10.
You're just gonna take this,
you're gonna get the plus 10 reward, you'll be done.
So that's the value of this arc here.
The value of this arc here,
we know that you're gonna basically get minus two
for taking that arc.
And you're gonna end up in a state
that's gonna get you 10 units of reward.
So the value of this arc is eight.
The value of this arc is zero.
So now we can actually be able to make decisions.
We can choose what's the optimal decision to take from here.
Well, clearly you would pick eight above zero.
So you would choose to take this arc over here.
Similarly, oh yeah, over here,
we didn't talk about the arc that goes down to the pub.
And the value of this arc,
and we'll see how to compute this in a minute,
is actually 8.4.
But once you've got this value,
you can say, so this arc is basically averaging
over all the things which might happen next,
and looking at the value of six, eight, and 10,
and weighing them.
And so now you can choose between,
well, should I go into a state
that gives me a reward of 10 units going onwards?
Or should I go to the pub,
where I get this nice plus one reward now,
and then still have a chance to get my 10?
Well, you have to weigh them up,
and it depends on the discount factor
and all these other things.
In this case, we see that this arc has a value of 10.
This arc has a value of 8.4.
So fortunately, it turns out,
I'm not recommending that you all go and drink beer,
and you stay and listen to the course.
Yeah, question.
There was a question earlier about,
in the minute, how many units it doesn't happen,
but what happens then if you have a positive cycle?
Say it published plus 100,
if you've been to the pub and studied in person,
or?
So I was talking about a Markov chain at that point.
Okay, so, yeah.
So if you've got,
there are technical conditions under which
reasonably defined Markov decision processes
are guaranteed to terminate.
So if you want to find out more about that,
there's a great book by Bert Seacast.
He goes into all the technical conditions
under which Markov decision processes are well-defined.
What we're going to talk about
is largely the discounted case,
because it's simpler.
So in the discounted case,
you don't need to worry about any of that stuff.
So if you do want to kind of remove discount factors
and consider the case
where you don't have discounting at all,
then you need to consider what happens
if you have infinite cycles and so forth,
and there's two ways to deal with that.
One of which is to look at all the technical conditions,
make sure your MDP satisfies those technical conditions.
The second case is basically to
actually use the average reward version
of reinforcement learning,
which is in the extension to this class.
If you have a large enough reward on a certain edge
for the first example,
even with a certain gamma,
there's nothing to put in plus power.
Yes.
Yeah, even if you put a gamma on the next one.
And then you go around and...
Yeah, I should have added...
So there were some technical conditions
to my answer earlier,
which were with certain probability transitions.
So with the transition probabilities we had before,
it wasn't possible to have infinite sequences.
Of course, if you have a self-cycle with probability one,
that does have an infinite cycle
that can be drawn from that sample.
So you have to have...
If you want to deal with discounts of one,
there's machinery you need,
and let's not worry about that.
Things are much easier when we have discounting.
Okay.
There wasn't this name because you knew the word.
Yes, yes, sorry.
So it's in all his books,
so Neurodynamic Programming is there,
but he has his new edition.
Probably the best place to look is volume two
of his new edition of his dynamic programming.
Yes.
What's that volume?
Yes, I think it's volume two that has this in.
Okay, so we've talked about optimal value function.
That doesn't...
So what we really care about,
what's the thing we really care about?
We care about the optimal policy.
So the optimal policy,
we need to understand what that really means.
What's the best possible way to behave in an MDP?
So we've talked about policies.
A policy is just like a stochastic mapping
and mapping from states to actions that we take.
And now we want to understand
well, what's the best one of these things?
So far, we've just talked about
how much juice we can extract from the system.
What's the maximum amount of reward we can get?
We haven't yet talked about the policy itself.
And so to understand what it means to be optimal,
we need to define a notion of optimality.
And to do that,
we need to know what it means for one policy
to be better than another policy.
And so what we do is we actually define
just a partial ordering over policies.
So this partial ordering basically tells us,
let's consider two policies,
pi and pi prime.
So these are two arbitrary policies.
And we're just gonna define this greater than
or equal to operator.
This is gonna be some partial ordering over policy space.
It basically tells us the intuitive thing.
Now one policy is better than another policy.
If the value function for that policy
is greater than the value function
for the other policy in all states.
So greater than or equal to in both cases.
So what this means is that it can't be worse.
That it's not possible to say a policy
is better than another policy.
If it's actually worse than that policy in one state.
Has to be at least as good in all states
for us to say that it's greater than or equal
in the partial ordering.
Okay, and then there's this very important theorem
which you'll find in Putnam and all the important texts
on NDPs.
And this basically tells us that for any MDP,
any MDP at all, there is an optimal policy
that is better than or equal to all other policies.
So you should think about that.
It's like, wow, okay, this is a good thing.
You don't end up with this weird situation
where sometimes you need to think about
taking this policy for a little bit of the MDP
and this other policy for a little bit of the MDP
and that that combination might be better.
There's always one unique policy.
Sorry, there's always at least one optimal policy,
pi star, not necessarily unique,
that is better than or equal to all other policies.
So there is always an optimal policy.
You can, this pi star tells you one way to behave in your MDP
that will extract the maximum juice from that MDP.
And we've already seen that that's true from the Q star.
Like if you have Q star and you pick the action
that chooses the arc with the biggest Q star,
that gives you one such policy.
Okay, but the theorem basically tells you
that that's true for any MDP,
that this really is the best thing
that you could find with the MDP.
There's not gonna be some other thing that's better
just by there's not like some weird averaging policy
that's gonna do better than this.
Furthermore, it is possible to have
more than one optimal policy.
So it's possible that, for example, the simplest case
is that imagine there's one action in your MDP
where there's two separate actions
that take you to the same state.
Doesn't really matter which one of those you take.
You're gonna end up in the same state.
They both can be optimal.
Doesn't matter which one of those you choose,
you're gonna get the same optimal value out of this MDP
whether you go left or go right.
Okay, so there can be more than one optimal policy,
but if they are optimal, then all optimal policies
achieve, they extract the same amount of reward
from the system, they get the same amount of juice.
So the value functions for those policies are the same.
Specifically, the amount of value that they get
can be given by the optimal value function,
by the optimal action value function, yeah.
Okay, so the value of pi star is actually
exactly the optimal value function that we defined earlier.
So the V star and the Q star that we defined
in the previous slides are precisely the numbers
that you extract if you try to evaluate the optimal policy.
So if you look at how good the optimal policy is,
then it is indeed the maximum amount
that we thought we could get out of the system.
So this is like a sanity theorem,
like all the things you would hope to be true are true,
and everything is sane,
and there is this thing called an optimal policy,
and it does give you the maximum amount
you can get from your MDP, okay.
So how do we find this thing?
Well, we've already seen this intuitively,
so this is just writing it down in equations,
it's just saying that all we need is,
you solve for Q star, and then you pick the action
that gives you the most Q star.
So in every state, what you do, if you're in state S,
well, you just pick the action A with probability one
that maximizes Q star, and that is the action
that will give you maximum possible reward.
And there is always a deterministic optimal policy.
So not only is there an optimal policy,
there's a deterministic optimal policy,
and this gives you one such deterministic optimal policy.
Okay, and the good thing about this is,
you know, once we've got Q star, we're done.
The game is solved, we're happy.
So let's do this one last time back at our student MDP.
So now what we're gonna look at is the optimal policy.
So now what we're looking at is these arcs,
remember, represent the actions that we can take,
like we can study or we can go to Facebook,
we can study or we can go to the pub.
And these red arcs now are highlighting
the optimal action value, the optimal policy,
pi star, is highlighted in red here.
This is the undiscounted case again.
So it's just this simple path all the way through our
studying and studying and studying again,
that we've already identified.
But we can see that it must be the case again
just by looking at the Q star values,
which are also highlighted in seeing that the optimal
policy is always the one that picks,
you know, but whenever you've got two choices,
it picks the one with the highest Q.
So specifically over here,
we've got the choice between Q star equals 10.
For studying again, Q star equals 8.4 for going to the pub.
So the optimal policy, the red arc,
is the one that maximizes that and gets us
the most reward going into the future.
Okay, so how do we arrive at this Q star in practice?
How do we actually arrive at
figuring out these Q star values?
These Q star values, we've seen time and again,
they're central.
This is the central quantity we're trying to figure out
so that we can just bang, hit the right action
without even any look ahead or further thought.
So once we have Q star, we're done.
We've solved the MDP, but how do we arrive at Q star?
So intuitively, what did we do?
Well, we kind of worked our way backwards.
We started off at this final state.
We looked at the value of taking this arc,
which was kind of trivially 10.
You go to here, you finish,
you get plus 10 along the way.
And then we worked our way backwards
and we kind of did this look ahead,
with a one step look ahead, where we started here
and we said, okay, we start here,
you look ahead one step, you end up with 10,
work your way backwards.
And that working backwards is precisely
what we get out of a Bellman equation.
So now what we're going to talk about
is a Bellman optimality equation.
So if you just open the textbook
and hear about the Bellman equation for MDPs,
they're talking about this one,
not the one we looked at before.
It's the Bellman optimality equation.
This is the one that tells you
how to really solve your MDP.
The one that tells you how do you relate
the optimal value function to itself.
So before we looked at the Bellman expectation equation
for MDPs, which told us how V pi related to itself.
So we looked at, for example,
under this average behavior policy
where you might go right or left with equal probability,
how did the values relate to themselves?
Now we're looking at really the optimal values.
We're looking at the best things.
We're looking at these,
something like these red highlighted guys,
like the values in these circles now,
six, six, eight, 10.
The maximum amount of juice you can get from your system,
how does that number relate to itself?
And what we can do is do like a one step look ahead again.
And so the way to understand this is again,
as one step look ahead, you start in,
you can ask, well, what's the optimal value
of being in some state?
Well, you can consider each of the actions
that you might take.
We'll take you to one of these chance nodes here,
one of these action nodes.
And we can say, when we reach that action,
we can look at the action value.
This is the red arc, the number on the red arc.
We can say this had a number on the red arc,
which was eight and this had a number on the red arc,
which was 10 or whatever it was.
And now what we do is instead of taking
the average of these guys,
we take the max over these guys.
So we're basically saying,
look at the value of each of the actions you can take
and pick the max of them.
And that's going to tell you how good it is
to be in this state here.
It's simply the max of all the Q values.
If I can go left, I can go right.
I look at how much reward I get in each case
and I pick the one that gives me the most.
So the value function of a state is the max
of the Q values of each of the actions
you can take from that state.
Okay.
Now we're going to do the other half.
So remember we had V going to Q,
now we're going to do Q going to V.
So now we want to know, well,
how good is one of those red arcs in that diagram?
How do we know what the optimal value is
for being in a particular state
and taking a particular action?
How do we know that the study arc
has a particular optimal value to it?
Well, again, we can do a one step look ahead.
But now we're looking ahead
of what the dynamics might do,
what the environment might do to us,
where the wind might blow us.
We don't control this.
This is like going to the pub
and then we don't know what will happen in the pub.
It's a crazy place and we might end up
in all of these different situations.
And each of those states that we end up in
has some optimal value.
So we kind of, this is like an inductive argument.
We sort of assume that we know inductively
the optimal value of each of those states
that we might end up in.
And if we know the value of each of those states
that we might end up in,
we just need to average over them now.
There's no max here.
We don't get to pick where the wind blows us.
We have to average over all the things
the environment might do to us.
And that tells us how good our action is.
So our action is the optimal action value.
It's just the immediate reward
plus the average over all the probability
that the wind might blow us left,
the probability that the wind might blow us right,
multiplied by the optimal value of being in that state.
Okay?
And again, what we can do is put those two pieces together.
When you put those two pieces together,
you have a recursive relationship
that relates V star to itself.
So this gives us an equation that we can solve.
Okay?
So this is now about two step look ahead.
We're looking ahead over the actions we can take here
and maximizing over those.
And we're also looking ahead over the dice
that the environment might roll.
And we don't maximize over the dice.
We don't control the dice.
Instead, we average over the dice
that the environment can roll.
We'll do this two step look ahead
over our actions from this state
and all the things the environment might do to us.
And then we look at the optimal value of where we end up.
We back these things all the way up
and that tells us how good it is to be in this state here.
So that's the Bellman optimality equation of V star.
Okay.
So finally, just before we give one last example,
we can do the same thing flipping the diagram around
and starting with the action values.
And this is to arrive at a recursive relationship
between the Q star values and themselves.
So this isn't really saying anything different
to the previous slide.
It's just like a reordering of the same idea.
And the reordering tells us that if we start,
and we want to know how good is one of these arcs,
how good is it to be in a particular state
and take a particular action.
Now, we first of all consider where the wind will blow us.
We average over the dice which the environment's rolling.
And wherever the dice roll, we get to make a decision.
So wherever the wind blows us,
we get to decide pick one action after that
and we get to maximize over the decisions we take.
So we average over the dice that we roll
and we maximize over the decisions we take.
And for each of these leaves,
we consider the action value,
the optimal action value, like how good is it to be
in this state taking this particular action
or in this state taking this action.
We back that up all the way to the beginning
and that tells us the Q value of the root of this diagram.
Okay.
So let's make that concrete
by picking one state in this diagram.
Probably stick to the teeth of this student MDP by now.
Anyway, I promise it won't come up too much again.
So here we start off in this state.
We consider, we have two possible actions that we can take.
So this one's rather straightforward.
There's no noise that in the environment,
we're not considering any dice rolls.
It's just like people said before,
implicitly there's like a,
the environment always rolls the same way
and takes us here if we take this action.
The environment always rolls the dice the same way
to take us here.
So we're just looking ahead one step
by saying that the value of this state, six,
and this is V star of this state, six,
is equal to the max over all the things we can do here
of the value function of where we end up.
So we know that inductively,
if we assume that these other values are correct,
then we assume that this has an optimal value of six,
this has an optimal value of eight.
So if we maximize over all the things we can do,
we see that that,
oh yeah, there's a minus two along the way as well.
So you can either get minus one
followed by ending up in a state with six.
So this has a value of five.
If we take this arc,
so Q star of this arc is five,
or this way we get minus two from our eight,
and we get six.
So we choose to go this way and our value function is six.
So how do we solve this in practice?
So previously we saw that we had these Bellman equations
with expectations that we could just solve
by doing matrix inversion.
So that's very appealing for those of you like MATLAB
and these nice tools where you can just type in your matrix,
type in your vector representing the rewards,
and bam, do your matrix inversion, you're done.
Unfortunately, that doesn't work
for optimizing the Bellman optimality equation
because we have these nonlinear equations now.
We've got a max in addition to our expectation,
and we have to solve for this equation
that relates V star to itself or Q star to itself
with a max of these expectations.
So in general, there's no close form to this thing,
and we have to be smarter.
And how do we be smarter?
Well, using iterative solution methods,
of which the best known examples are value iteration,
policy iteration, which we'll talk about in the next class.
These are dynamic programming methods
for iterative dissolving these recursive equations,
and Q learning, which we'll talk about
in our subsequent lecture.
That's awesome.
The matrix solution itself
is implicitly iterative underneath.
You don't get away from doing any sort of iterative calculation.
I mean, to solve that matrix equation,
it's in order, I think, you properly will have
to iterate in some sense to get a solution.
Well, I mean, there's computation required
to solve the matrix, and there's steps to that computation,
but it's not.
So by iterative solution method,
we mean something more like where you have an equation
which you iteratively apply at each step,
you can apply the next step of that update.
So you start with some estimate,
you update your estimate towards a new estimate, and so forth.
Now, of course, there are iterative approaches
to matrix inversion, like the Sherman Morrison trick,
which can be applied to reinforcement learning as well.
So there are cases where the matrix inversion
can be reduced in complexity from n cubed to n squared.
Those are special cases,
as I'm talking about the general approach here.
So yes and no.
Okay, so just about out of time,
I think I want to really just take questions
and make sure people are following
rather than going into the extensions in any great detail.
So this is a great time,
if you feel that something was unclear,
and now's your chance to ask.
Otherwise, I'm just going to assume that,
you know, that's all the notes were incredibly perfectly clear
and everyone understood everything,
which I'm very confident is not true.
Yes, please.
So we should have an imperfect moment
or a missing information.
I don't know how that translates to a diagram of the end
which we would have missing moment,
or what you have to do in the solution,
where you should have a 51,
or the one with, you know, enlivening by someone.
Okay, so it's a great question.
So the question is, you know, in reality,
the MDP is just a model.
We're trying to model some real phenomenon
out in the world, some real environment.
How do we represent the fact that our model is imperfect?
We're actually going to have a class on
where we'll talk about model-based reinforcement learning.
If there's time,
I'll talk about some of the approaches to uncertainty.
So some of the classical approaches to uncertainty
include explicitly representing the uncertainty in the MDP.
So you could be Bayesian, for example,
have some posterior estimate of what the MDP dynamics are,
and then solve not just one single MDP,
but a whole distribution over MDPs,
and find the policy that's optimal with respect to all of them.
That's computationally very difficult.
Another approach is to actually factor in the uncertainty
in your representation of what's going on in the world
into your MDP itself.
So you'll say you're in a state where,
not only am I in a state where my robot's here,
but I'm in a state where my robot's here,
and I think that the world has these dynamics,
or I'm in a state where the robot's here,
and I've seen these observations so far,
which implicitly tell me something about the uncertainty
of what's going on in the MDP.
So that can be much more tractable.
You don't necessarily need to explicitly reason
about all the uncertainty in the environment,
but it's maybe a little less intuitive
to understand the form of the uncertainty.
The uncertainty isn't made explicit.
And then maybe the only other thing to say,
which we already touched on,
is that sometimes it's sufficient to just say,
well, except that our model is imperfect,
and use a discount factor to capture the fact
that we've got some uncertainty.
You can also make the discount factor variable
to represent the fact that you're more uncertain
in some states than others.
So you don't have to have 0.9 everywhere.
You could have 0.9 in one state,
0.99 in another state,
representing how bad your model is in that situation.
So it's a very active research area.
I think it's a great question.
Yeah.
So everything we've shown us today
seems to sort of get towards maximizing reward.
But is there anything implicit in there
that would also have a consideration of risk?
So if you, you might be interested in maximizing your reward
at a future time in choosing that policy,
but there might be some chance
of choosing that policy,
you know, that there's also an increased risk.
Okay, so the question is,
everything's just talking about maximizing reward
and expectations of those reward
without explicitly considering risk
or variance of those returns.
So I think the correct answer to that
is to say that you can always transform any MDP
with no risk into,
so if there's some amount that you care about your risk,
like let's say that there's a cost
that depends on the variance of your returns,
there is another MDP which has a different reward function
that already factors in the variance of those rewards
into the actual reward that you see
at the end of your trajectory.
So that can be implicit in this model
you've shown us deliberately?
There is a transformation of any risk sensitive MDP
into another MDP.
However, that transformation can be quite complex.
So you might need to remember
all the things that you've seen so far
and it can be a more complicated MDP
that you end up having to solve.
So that's the first answer.
The second answer is to say that a bunch of people
do specifically consider risk sensitive MDPs
where you don't just consider expectations,
but you consider what's the variance of those rewards
at the end of the day.
So there's a bunch of work out there
and I'm happy to give you pointers to that
if you're interested.
Any other questions?
Okay, one more and then I just want to say
a couple of words before everyone piles up.
Oh, yeah, sorry, this guy was actually waiting for longer to say.
Some example, for instance, I mean, obviously,
there are two parts, balance,
and it's only just pure mass.
And in the last situation, for instance,
in finance, where somebody will actually balance it,
you know, in terms of arbitration.
But in terms of like real creation,
a real situation, like the robot,
or like a private unit,
what does it mean to, you know,
Okay, so the question is,
what's the intuition behind the Bellman equation
in some real example?
So if we take the Atari game as an example,
so the Bellman optimality equation,
let's focus on that one,
that's the crux of where we got to,
the Q star or V star is telling you,
you know, what's the maximum amount of score you can get,
you know, you're in this screen here,
what's the maximum score you can get from this screen here?
And the intuition is that all you need to do
to get that maximum score,
this is called the principle of optimality.
So the principle of optimality tells you
that the way to get the maximum score
is to behave optimally for one step,
and then to behave optimally
for the remainder of your trajectory.
Okay, if you behave optimally
for the remainder of your trajectory,
that's the value function
from the state that you end up in.
And so now all you need to do
is to figure out,
well, how do I behave optimally for one step?
And the way that you behave optimally for one step
is to maximize over those optimal value functions
in the places you might end up in.
So it's like you might move your,
you might move Pac-Man to the left,
and you might move Pac-Man to the right.
If you move Pac-Man to the right,
and you can get 100 points of optimal value
from that point onwards,
or so moving to the right,
you might get plus 10,
and then 100 points of optimal value afterwards.
Moving to the left, you might get plus 20,
but then only 50 points of optimal value afterwards.
And so the intuition is that
just by breaking down your trajectory
into these two parts,
into the optimal decision at one step,
and the optimal decision from there onwards,
you can describe what it means
to have optimal dynamics for the whole problem.
Okay.
One more question,
and I just want to say a couple of words
about the extensions,
but without any details at all,
so don't get scared.
Yes?
So, if you have a million states,
and a million actions per state,
you have a large MDP,
and so now you're asking how do you,
how do you actually solve the MDP
to find the optimal value function?
Is that the question?
Was the question,
how do you solve it,
or how do you decide on the immediate rewards?
I see.
So the question isn't how do you solve the MDP,
it's how do you model the MDP,
how do you represent a large MDP.
So typically the reward function
is given by the environment dynamics,
so it's given by,
so for example it might be,
imagine you're playing Atari,
the score that you get,
there are many more than the million states in Atari,
and yet the score is just a function
of that state that you're in,
so it's something which you're in this state,
you query the emulator,
you say what's the score,
or you extract the score from the screen,
and it's just a function that depends on your state.
So typically there's some function
mapping state to reward,
and that function characterizes like the,
this is like, you know,
imagine you're a programmer
and you're trying to tell your program
how to, what the problem is you're trying to solve.
The reward function is kind of like
the definition of the program,
you're asking the programmer to solve
this particular problem,
it's part of the problem definition.
So the reward is just a function of the,
it's part of the environment,
it's part of the thing describing
how the environment state gets mapped into reward.
So in any reasonable problem,
you'll see that there's a way to transform this
and describe the reward normally quite conveniently.
There's a big open question,
which is how do you best model the reward
in a way that actually leads to intuitively
what we as humans think of as the best solution.
Okay, very briefly,
I just wanted to put up this slide
just to highlight that there are some additional slides,
extensions to MVPs,
this is not examinable material,
I do not expect you guys to go off and revise stuff
which I haven't told you about.
And in general for these classes,
I'll try to make it very clear
what's not examinable material.
And if we run out of time at any point,
don't panic, you know,
you won't suddenly find a question
to crop up in the exam which we didn't cover.
But the extensions are on the slide
just there as additional material,
in particular telling you how to deal with
infinite MVPs, continuous MVPs,
partially observable MVPs,
undiscounted average reward MVPs.
These are the major extensions to the MVP framework.
Just to give you some sense,
I think just out of interest,
you can get some sense, it's not details,
it's just a brief outline,
showing you how you can move beyond this
to the case where you're trying to control
some real airplane or helicopter
with continuous actions
and perhaps even continuous time steps.
Or where the state that you see
doesn't tell you everything about the environment,
but you just get to see like the robot's camera
at every given time step
and you don't get exposed to the Markov state
that's actually inside the environment,
you just get to see what your agent sees at that moment.
And finally the case where,
we can deal with undiscounted cases,
I basically looking at a limiting case
where we average over,
where we look at the average reward going into the future,
the average reward per time step,
instead of the discounted sum of rewards.
It's a different definition of return
that actually works out very neatly.
So just if you're feeling enthusiastic,
go and have a look, there's pointers to elsewhere.
And otherwise, the remainder is,
next week we'll start to talk about how to solve these things.
So this is just defining the problem.